Okay, today's דף Daf is דף עז, Daf ayin zayin, seventy-seven, and
we take it, we resume at the very top, first line of
seventy-seven. And the issue here had been the גמרא Gemara is like
working like on a source that was quoted in passing, so just
to like for figuring it out, not directly related to the major
theme here of the question about like
about מביאים קדשים לבית הפסול, Mevim kodashim l'veis hapsul, but anyway. But
the גמרא Gemara says a case where somebody doesn't know if he's
a מצורע, Metzora, so he brings an אשם, Asham, stipulates that if
he's not a מצורע Metzora the אשם Asham will serve as a
שלמים, Shelamim, and then you treat the animal, the קרבן Korban like
the stringent of both of those sacrifices. And then the גמרא Gemara
says, what do you do about the לוג Log of oil? So
it says well, you bring that, and you treat it both as
the לוג Log that you use for the purification of the מצורע
Metzora and a לוג Log that would be a נדבה Nedavah free-will
sacrifice sort of like a מנחה Mincha where you take a קומץ
Kometz of it and you put it on the מזבח Mizbeach and
put it on the altar. So the גמרא Gemara had to figure
out how you can do both things with the לוג. Log. And
basically the conclusion of the גמרא Gemara was that you take the
oil, you put it on the altar, according to תוספות Tosfos the
question of the גמרא Gemara is, but one minute, if it's מצורע
Metzora oil, then you're not allowed to burn, you know, something designated
for מצורע Metzora oil on the altar. That's this prohibition of קדש
ממנו לאישים, Kodesh mimenu l'ishin, something that was going to be used
in a different context of a sacrifice you can't burn on the
altar. So the answer is, yeah, you just burn it as fuel,
you know, not as a, in case it happens to not actually
be a מנחה, Mincha, you know a נדבה, Nedavah, in case it
happens to be מצורע Metzora oil. So you burn that on the
altar, then you refill the oil, and then you use the oil
in the process of sprinkling. For רש"י Rashi then the question was,
one minute, since some of this was already offered on the altar,
if this is not מצורע Metzora oil, if this is actually נדבה
Nedavah oil, how can now it's leftover from the fire and how
can you use it in this other ritual? And the answer also
was, well, you just say if it's not really needed for מצורע
Metzora we'll just treat it like as water, it doesn't mean anything
and so on. Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara says the following,
top of עז עמוד א. Ayin zayin amud aleph.
ואיכא שיריים דבעי מכלינהו, V'ika shiyayim d'ba'i michlinehu, I'll read the word
on the side is מכלינהו. Michlinehu. ואיכא הך פורתא דלא קמיצי ליה.
V'ika hach purta d'lo kamitzei lei. One minute. What are you going
to do with the remnant of the oil after you're done with
all of these procedures? You're going to eat it, right? But remember
we poured extra oil in here at stage number two, in case
we needed to use this for מצורע. Metzora. But in the scenario
that this is actually נדבה Nedavah oil, so the קומץ Kometz that
you took was by what remained. This extra oil that was added
which has to be sanctified because you're using it also for the
מצורע, Metzora, okay,
never was part of this נדבה Nedavah process, never had a קומץ
Kometz taken from it. So how can you eat from the extra
oil that was added assuming the scenario that it was actually נדבה
Nedavah oil and not מצורע Metzora oil? So that's the גמרא's Gemara
question. ואיכא שיריים, V'ika shiyayim, the remnant that's left over דבעי מכלינהו,
d'ba'i michlinehu, I'm going to read מכלינהו Michlinehu but it could mean
מילינהו Milinehu you have to refill it. ואיכא הך פורתא דלא קמיצי
ליה, V'ika hach purta d'lo kamitzei lei, and that extra bit that
you added you never took the קומץ Kometz on it. So the
גמרא Gemara says דפריק ליה, D'parik lei, fine. What you do is
you say, in case this was a נדבה Nedavah if this was
מצורע Metzora oil we refilled this, used it, the remnant of everything
gets eaten by the כהנים. Kohanim. If it was נדבה Nedavah oil,
this extra stuff was added after it had been used as a
נדבה Nedavah and had been sanctified, so we're going to say if
in the scenario that it was נדבה Nedavah oil, you'll stipulate and
say in the scenario that this was נדבה Nedavah oil, that extra
bit that was added is going to be redeemed on this money,
and then you're going to use that money for another נדבה, Nedavah,
okay, so you redeem it. Now רש"י Rashi is bothered because once
something is sanctified, what?
How does that help?
No, because then you'll be eating this oil, and this oil will
be ninety percent נדבה Nedavah oil that had a קומץ Kometz taken
from it, and ten percent חולין Chullin that's mixed in. Okay, because
you're only redeeming the percentage that was added afterwards. Alright, so you
don't need a קומץ Kometz taken on it, now it's חולין. Chullin.
And then what about מביא חולין לעזרה? Mevi chullin l'azarah?
So that's the גמרא's Gemara question. But before we get to that,
רש"י Rashi says you're also not allowed to redeem something that was
already sanctified in a כלי שרת. Kli sharet. So רש"י Rashi says,
well, but a כלי שרת Kli sharet אינו מקדש אלא לדעת. eino
mekadesh ela l'daat. You have to want it to work, the כלי
שרת. Kli sharet. So when you add this oil, you basically say,
if I'm adding this oil, if the guy's a מצורע, Metzora, I'm
adding this oil and it's now going to be fully sanctified through
a כלי שרת, Kli sharet, not just verbally, and I'm going to
use it for the מצורע Metzora ritual. If the guy isn't a
מצורע, Metzora, then I'm adding this oil, but I don't want the
כלי שרת Kli sharet to sanctify it, and after we're done with
the מצורע Metzora ritual, I'm going to redeem that extra oil on
money and use that money for something for another נדבה. Nedavah. This
is the גמרא. Gemara. Oh my god, you just go through a
checklist. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara asks the question, one minute, now you have some
חולין Chullin oil mixed up. והא קא, V'ha ka,
so the גמרא Gemara
says היכא פריק ליה, Heicha parik lei,
where are you going to redeem it? אי גואי, Ei gava'ei, if
the oil is going to be inside the Temple when you redeem
it, קא מייתי חולין לעזרה, Kamaitei chullin l'azarah, you're bringing חולין Chullin
into the עזרה. Azarah. Now this idea of bringing חולין Chullin into
the... Am I bringing חולין בעזרה chullin b'azarah because there's some non-sanctified
food? It's possible. But it's always easier to understand that the problem
is you're bringing it in in a ritual sacrificial context. So here
too, even though you've redeemed it in this scenario, but the bottom
line is you're having it here in sort of, you know, in
this larger sacrificial context. So how is that allowed to redeem it
and then have חולין chullin in the עזרה azarah in that way?
So the גמרא Gemara says אי אבראי i avrai and if you
take the oil out of the עזרה azarah and then you redeem
the חולין chullin oil, the extra oil that's mixed in, איפסולי ביוצא
ipsulei b'yotzei the whole oil becomes invalid because it's being brought out
of the עזרה. azarah. So אלא גואי ella gavai fine, the oil's
on the inside of the עזרה. azarah. וחולין ממילא הויין v'chullin mimeila
havyan
and it's not a problem, you didn't bring it in when it
was not sanctified, you brought it in when it was sanctified, now
that you turned it into חולין, chullin, that's not really that transgression,
and that just happened sort of it didn't really happen by itself,
you turned it into חולין, chullin, but you didn't bring it, you
didn't bring it as חולין chullin into the עזרה, azarah, you brought
it as something sanctified into the עזרה, azarah, and while it was
already in the עזרה azarah it became חולין. chullin. Okay so now
the גמרא Gemara says ואמר רבי שמעון אין מתנדבים שמן. v'amar Rabbi
Shimon ein mitnadvim shemen. So now we've got another problem. Fine, we
figured out all this procedure. But now remember what you stipulated is
you say this is going to be מצורע metzora oil, and if
I don't need this as מצורע metzora oil, this is going to
be נדבה nedavah oil, like a free will sacrifice it'll operate like
a מנחה. minchah. But one minute, this is going according to רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon himself says that לכתחילה
lechatchila you don't give שמן shemen as a נדבה. nedavah. So how
do you do this? So the גמרא's Gemara answer again is תיקוני
גברא שאני. tikunei gavra shani. No, we have to save this guy,
get him out of his מצורע metzora status, so we're able to
do things that לכתחילה lechatchila we otherwise wouldn't do. בדיעבד bedi'avad it
certainly works to have a sacrifice like this, an oil sacrifice, and
therefore even רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would allow it here because we're
sort of backed into a corner. Okay now יתיב רב רחומי yasiv
Rav Rechumi Rav Rechumi was sitting קמיה דרבינא kamei d'Ravina in front
of Ravina, ויתיב וקאמר משמיה דרב הונא בר תחליפא v'yasiv v'ka'amar mishmei
d'Rav Huna bar Tachlifa and he said over the following question going
back again to this whole scenario where we're finally moving beyond the
oil. We dealt all this discussion was to figure out how to
handle the oil. But remember the first line was that this guy's
obligated in an אשם, asham, and therefore you stipulate and you say
either it's an אשם asham and if you don't need it as
an אשם asham it's a שלמים, shlamim, because a שלמים shlamim is
free will. Okay and therefore you can always stipulate and make it
into a שלמים, shlamim, and a שלמים shlamim could be male the
same way an אשם asham is male. So רב רחומי Rav Rechumi
was saying and he said the following
in the name
of רב הונא בר תחליפא, Rav Huna bar Tachlifa, ונימא אשם זה
יהא אשם תלוי. v'neima asham zeh yehei asham talui. Okay, he says
I don't get it, why do you have to go to a
שלמים shlamim and then say oh we have to treat it strictly
as both a שלמים shlamim and an אשם? asham? You could say
either I'll make this an אשם מצורע asham metzora if I'm a
מצורע, metzora, and if not I'm not a מצורע metzora I'll make
it an אשם תלוי. asham talui. An אשם תלוי asham talui is
an אשם asham you bring in a case of a doubtful sin.
Now normally the doubtful sin is when there's something concrete. I ate
this thing and now I'm told that it might have been חלב.
chelev. I thought it was kosher fat, it might have been חלב.
chelev. Some say it has to even be more concrete. There has
to have been חלב chelev and kosher fat in front of me
and I don't know which one I ate. Okay, but that's an
אשם תלוי. asham talui. But there's an opinion of רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer that since we always are dealing with the possibility that we've
sinned and we don't know about it, you can at any day
of any day you want just bring an אשם תלוי asham talui
because of the possibility that you might have sinned even if you
don't have a concrete basis for being concerned about that. So according
to that opinion, why doesn't this מצורע metzora just say either this
will be my אשם מצורע asham metzora or it'll be an אשם
תלוי asham talui and stay within the family of אשם? asham? Okay,
שמע מינה shma mina now since we didn't give that option we
should infer מאן תנא דפליג עליה דרבי אליעזר רבי שמעון. man tanna
d'palig alei d'Rabbi Eliezer Rabbi Shimon. Since this משנה mishna is רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon didn't give the option
of just stipulating that it could be an אשם תלוי, asham talui,
he had to go all the way to a שלמים, shlamim, from
here we can infer that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon doesn't hold of
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon holds you cannot
just סתם stam give an אשם תלוי, asham talui, you need something
more concrete. And that's why we didn't give that as an option.
Okay, that seems pretty reasonable, that would have been a logical option
of an אשם תלוי, asham talui, it must be that you're not
allowed to סתם stam give an אשם תלוי. asham talui. So אמר
ליה amar lei so רבינא Ravina said to this, תורה תורה, Torah
Torah, what happened to the Torah? Like this great Rabbi Rav Huna
made this whole דיוק diyuk from the fact that we didn't opt
to say you could have done an אשם תלוי, asham talui, what
was going on in his mind? אימי בדכרי מחלפי לך? imi b'dachrei
michalfei lach?
Did it get mixed up to you the difference between like a
sheep and a ram?
An אשם asham of a מצורע, metzora, right, is a
one-year-old sheep, the same way a שלמים shlamim could be, but an
אשם תלוי asham talui is a two-year-old ram. So what do you
mean oh why don't you just stipulate either this will be an
אשם מצורע asham metzora or an אשם תלוי? asham talui? One is
a sheep and one is a ram. You couldn't make it one
or the other. You have to start with a sheep, so the
only other thing the sheep could be is a שלמים. Shlamim. That's
why he stipulated a שלמים. Shlamim. He couldn't have stipulated let it
be an אשם תלוי, Asham Taluy, it has no, not based at
all on whether you can bring an אשם תלוי Asham Taluy based
on just you know non-concrete you know concerns. It has to do
with the fact that it can't be an אשם תלוי Asham Taluy
because it's a sheep and an אשם תלוי Asham Taluy has to
be a ram. So like yeah how did this great great rabbi
make that obvious mistake? You know you can understand it sometimes you're
so caught up in the hypothetical possibilities, theoretical possibilities that you actually
forget the concrete specifics of like you know sheep versus ram. Okay
so that was the end of that whole digression, that whole point
was about figuring out whether when רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says he's
not concerned when things get mixed up, you know just eat it
like the overlapping stringent categories, and the rabbis say back no that
would just make you have to אין מביאין קדשים לבית הפסול, Ein
mevi'in kodashim l'veit hapsul,
it might have to make you finish eating it sooner than sooner
than you otherwise would, and so the rabbis say therefore if you
have an alternative you should do the alternative, the alternative here would
be wait till it gets a blemish and redeem it, but רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon said no no no you can do it. And
then the question was did רב שמעון Rab Shimon say you could
do it because because it's already mixed up? Or did he even
לכתחילה lechatchila was not concerned about this issue about מביאין קדשים לבית
הפסול? mevi'in kodashim l'veit hapsul? And the evidence seemed to be that
it was not even a concern of his לכתחילה. lechatchila. That he
really was not concerned, you could do this thing, you could sort
of you know buy תרומה Terumah with שביעית Shevi'it money, you could
put תרומה Terumah spices into a קרבן, Korban, like he did not
seem to be worried about this concern, you'll just be responsible, you'll
make sure that it doesn't become a problem. Okay now we go
on to the next משנה, Mishnah, which is rather than the animals
getting mixed up of different sacrifices we have the actual cut up
pieces of meat getting mixed up. Okay. אברי חטאת שנתערבו באברי עולה.
Eivrei Chatat shenitarvu b'eivrei Olah.
So the אברים, eivarim, the cut up limbs of the sacrifice of
a חטאת Chatat which the כהנים Kohanim were going to cook and
eat, and then the limbs of an עולה Olah which was going
to be burnt on the altar get mixed up. So what do
you do? The כהנים Kohanim can't eat it, they might be eating
עולה Olah meat, right? That would be like a terrible violation. So
but what are you going to do? Burn it up on the
altar? But then you're burning חטאת Chatat meat which should be eaten
by the כהנים. Kohanim. So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר omer יתן
למעלה. yitein l'ma'ala. No go ahead it's fine put the חטאת Chatat
meat on the fire on the on the altar. ורואה אני את
בשר החטאת מלמעלה כאילו הן עצים. V'ro'eh ani et b'sar hachatat milma'ala
k'ilu hen eitzim. This is what we quoted at the end of
yesterday, and I will just say any meat here that is the
חטאת Chatat meat, I can't identify which is which, I'm not putting
it up as a form of like לריח ניחוח, l'reiach nicho'ach, I'm
not putting it up to offer it to God, I'm putting it
up as fuel. Okay. The meat here that's עולה Olah meat is
an offering to God, the meat here that's חטאת Chatat meat is
fuel for the fire. וחכמים אומרים Vachachamim omrim and the sages say
no, we don't accept this idea just pretend it's fuel. Meat on
the fire is a problem if it's if it's not being offered
to God and if it's חטאת Chatat meat. And therefore they say
תעבור צורתן ויצאו לבית השריפה. Te'avor tzuratan v'yeitzu l'veit hasreifah. Let its
literally its visage become transformed meaning let it let it decay but
it's not physically decay it's a way of saying let it wait
till the next day so halachically it's נותר. notar. And halachically once
it's נותר notar then it has an obligation to burn it and
you let everything including the עולה, Olah, well you don't know which
is which, you let everything become נותר. notar. Okay and then you
burn it. Of course the question is how are you allowed to
let it become נותר? notar? It's a violation, לא תותירו ממנו, lo
totiru mimenu, right? You're not allowed to. So they must assume that
like שב ואל תעשה. shev v'al ta'aseh. Yeah שב ואל תעשה shev
v'al ta'aseh is still a violation. It's interesting the גמרא's Gemara not
going to ask that question, like how are you allowed to actively
let something become נותר? notar? They must assume that if you're doing
it because you have no choice, right, so you know you're not
choosing to make it נותר, notar, you have no option, you're an
אנוס. onus. There's nothing you're able to do with it. If halachically
you're not allowed to burn it on the altar then your hands
are tied. Okay so it all becomes נותר notar and then you
go ahead and then you're allowed to burn it. The interesting thing
also for רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is that he's bothered by the
idea that you're not supposed to burn something as an offering to
God, you know like the meat of a חטאת Chatat and he
says we'll just pretend that it's fuel. One minute we'll just pretend
that it's fuel. But what he's not bothered about is that you're
destroying חטאת Chatat meat, meaning I don't know that's not exactly technically
the same as like מעילה, me'ilah, it's not the same as misuse.
Like let's say the כהן Kohen took the חטאת Chatat meat that
he had, you know and he just decided for himself to like
he was roasting it and then he said ah whatever I'm not
hungry anymore and he took it off the spit and he just
threw it straight in the fire, you know in the עזרה Azarah
there, whatever and he סתם stam destroyed. Is there an איסור issur
of destroying חטאת Chatat meat? So you know it doesn't seem obviously
proper but it might not be as concrete of an איסור. issur.
So that doesn't seem to be the גמרא's Gemara concern. The concern
is not that you're destroying it, the concern is that you seem
to be offering it on the altar and this is not something
that is supposed to be offered and the answer is you treat
it as fuel. And the חכמים Chachamim say better to just let
it all become נותר, notar, we're going to ignore the fact that
you're not allowed to let things become נותר, notar, we presumably your
hands are tied here and after it becomes נותר notar then you
actually have a license to burn it and destroy it outside the
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, which is what the בית השריפה Beit HaSreifah
means, outside the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Yes, Michael. So before we
were mixing the oil with the... Yeah, you're basically. Yeah, I mean
that's implicit. The when it says לשם עצים, l'shem etzim, that's what
it means. But you said רואה אני ro'eh ani earlier. Eventually here
it says רואה אני. ro'eh ani. That's true. That's true. The we're
going to quote a ברייתא braisa which we quoted yesterday that just
says לשם. l'shem. Okay. So let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. Yes, Michael, and Aaron's sons when they burned that, wasn't it
a חטאת chatas that they allowed to be burned? Yeah, they burnt
it, but right, it's similar, they burnt it because it somehow became
invalid. So there you have that idea. Something becomes invalid, you burn
it. מאי טעמא דרבי אליעזר? Mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Eliezer? What's the reason
of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
that you're allowed to do this? אמר קרא ואל המזבח לא יעלו
לריח ניחוח. Amar kra ve'el hamizbe'ach lo ya'alu l'rei'ach nicho'ach. Okay, so
this is the פסוק pasuk actually it was one
that we were also referring to yesterday. I should quote the whole
פסוק pasuk because it's, we're going to דרשן darshen parts of it.
Thank you. 2:12. What? 2:12. It says like this, it says, כי
כל שאור וכל דבש לא תקטירו ממנו אשה להשם. ki kol se'or
vechol devash lo taktiru mimenu isheh l'Hashem. So this is specifically to
move my beautiful picture.
Pictures really help, don't they?
It's so easy for keeping things straight. Okay. כי כל שאור, ki
kol se'or, this is 3:11, וכל דבש לא תקטירו ממנו אשה להשם.
vechol devash lo taktiru mimenu isheh l'Hashem. And then it says קרבן
ראשית, korban reishis, okay, קרבן ראשית תקריבו אותם להשם.
korban reishis
takrivu osam l'Hashem. So now this is קרבן ראשית תקריבו אותם להשם,
korban reishis takrivu osam l'Hashem, תקריבו אותם להשם, takrivu osam l'Hashem, ואל
המזבח לא יעלו
לריח ניחוח.
ve'el hamizbe'ach lo
ya'alu l'rei'ach nicho'ach.
So don't bring something that is like fermented and sweet on the
altar. Okay, this is לא תקטירו, lo taktiru, don't burn it on
the altar. You can bring it as a first offerings, but don't
put it on the altar. So what's the first offerings? So we
say that this basically means ביכורים. Bikkurim. Okay, so you bring ביכורים,
Bikkurim, you sort of bring it, you wave it, whatever, but you
don't put it on the altar. Also רש''י Rashi says
לחם הפנים, lechem hapanim, that's the שאור, se'or, what that exactly has
to
do with, what do
you call it,
the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim was מצה. matzah.
Anyway, okay. Anyway,
that's basically. שתי הלחם? Shtei halechem? שתי הלחם, Shtei halechem, I think.
But רש''י, Rashi, I
think says, maybe I misread רש''י. Rashi.
שתי הלחם, Shtei halechem, I'm sorry,
I misread רש''י. Rashi. Thank you. Because לחם הפנים lechem hapanim is
מצה. matzah. Okay, so שתי הלחם shtei halechem which is also, and
both of these are brought, right? I mean שתי הלחם shtei halechem
is brought on שבועות, Shavuos, דבש תמרים dvash temarim whatever, ביכורים Bikkurim
is brought around that time. Okay, anyway, so these you can bring
as an offering or whatever, but you don't actually burn them on
the, you don't burn
them on the altar.
Okay, but the way we're reading it, and this is what we
read yesterday, was לא תקטירו ממנו. lo taktiru mimenu. What are the
things you're not allowed to burn on the altar? So it says,
so what you're not allowed to burn is, what can't you burn?
לא תקטירו, lo taktiru, excuse me, what can't you burn? What you
can't burn is ממנו אשה להשם. mimenu isheh l'Hashem. Something that from
it was something offered to the altar. So let's talk about the
remnant of a מנחה minchah or the remnant of the oil that
we spoke before. Something from it was put on the altar, ממנו,
mimenu, from it something was put, was burnt on the altar, the
remnant of the מנחה, minchah, and therefore don't burn that, what was
left over, don't burn it. Okay, so that's the idea. Don't burn
things that aren't supposed to be burnt, that something else was sort
of offered already. So similarly a חטאת, chatas, a חטאת, chatas, ממנו
אשה להשם, mimenu isheh l'Hashem, the fat and the entrails of the
חטאת chatas was burned as an אשה. isheh. לא תקטירו, lo taktiru,
but you're not allowed to burn the actual meat of the חטאת.
chatas. But Rashi says you do burn the meat. What? I know,
so we have to
make, figure out
how you're going to work make it work. But this is the
problem. You can't burn the part of a sacrifice, some part was
offered on the altar, don't burn the other part. That was the
issue we dealt with yesterday. That's the issue we're dealing with now.
How can you burn the meat of a חטאת? chatas? So the
גמרא Gemara says מאי טעמא
דרבי אליעזר?
Mai
ta'ama d'Rabbi Eliezer? אמר קרא ואל המזבח לא יעלו לריח ניחוח.
Amar
kra
ve'el hamizbe'ach lo ya'alu l'rei'ach nicho'ach. Because of the end of it.
לריח ניחוח, L'rei'ach nicho'ach, לא יעלו. lo ya'alu. The problem is if
you're going to burn this לריח ניחוח. l'rei'ach nicho'ach. Not just burning
it is the problem, burning it for the sake of a pleasing
odor, for the sake of offering it to God. If you burn
it in a different context, it'll be acceptable. לריח ניחוח אי אתה
מעלה אבל אתה מעלה לשם עצים. l'rei'ach nicho'ach ee atah ma'aleh aval
atah ma'aleh l'shem etzim. ורבנן, Verabbanan, and the rabbis say, מיעט רחמנא
אותם. mi'eit rachmana osam. Okay. קרבן ראשית תקריבו אותם. Korban reishis takrivu
osam. So they say here's the word אותם osam להשם, l'Hashem, meaning,
yes, I agree with your דרשה. drasha. If you put it on
the fire as firewood you don't violate. But what is that referring
to? That's referring to the פשט pshat of the פסוק, pasuk, the
שאור וכל דבש. se'or v'chol dvash. So if you put a fruit
or חמץ chametz on the altar and you did it for the
sake of firewood, that's okay. This means this last thing here means
firewood is okay. Okay? This is ironic. It's something you're not allowed
to put on at all if you put it on. Right. The
thing that is explicitly prohibited you're allowed to treat as firewood. The
stuff that's like a דרשה drasha you're not. I know it is
bizarre. Okay, so we agree with your דרשה drasha that firewood
is okay, but that's
only about the thing the פסוק pasuk is talking about explicitly. If
you treat the חמץ chametz or the fruit as firewood you're okay.
If you treat the remnant of a sacrifice as firewood you're not
okay. All right? Yes, it is very ironic. Okay. מיעט miat רחמנא
Rachmana אותם. otam. אותם otam הוא hu דלא d'lo עלה aleh לריח
ניחוח. l'reiach nichoach. Those, the שאור se'or and the דבש, dvash, you
can't do as a
ריח ניחוח reiach nichoach but you can do as firewood. אבל aval
אתה ata מעלה ma'aleh לשם עצים. l'shem eitzim. אבל aval מידי אחריני,
midi achrinei, something else, the remnant of a sacrifice which is the
דרשה drasha of the פסוק, pasuk, לא, lo, you don't have a
היתר heter to do it for the sake of firewood. ורבי אליעזר,
v'Rabbi Eliezer, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer will say back, אותם otam הוא
hu דרבאי d'rabai לך lach כבש kevesh כמזבח, k'mizbe'ach, אבל aval מידי
אחריני midi achrinei לא. lo. Ah, there's a הלכה halacha that אל
המזבח לא יעלו לריח ניחוח. el hamizbe'ach lo ya'alu l'reiach nichoach. What
if you put them not on the actual top of the altar
but you just put them on the ramp? We have a debate
about whether that's considered like being on the altar. Yeah. So what
he says is this אותם otam is saying
when you're dealing this makes more sense, let's keep the thing that's
more explicit more strict, not more lenient. The stuff that's more explicit,
the חמץ chametz and the fruit, they can't even be put not
only on
the מזבח mizbe'ach they can't even be put on the ramp. אל
המזבח el hamizbe'ach they can't even be put on the ramp. The
other stuff that's inferred from here, the remnant of a sacrifice, there
the prohibition is only on the מזבח mizbe'ach proper. Okay? אבל aval
מידי אחריני midi achrinei לא. lo. ורבנן v'Rabbanan תרתי שמע מינה. tarti
shma mina. Both we learn out from it. אותם otam says the
whole all of the sort of inferences from the verse are limited
to the to the honey and to the bread. So honey and
bread number one they're more strict that only they are prohibited on
the ramp, remnants of sacrifice are not prohibited on the ramp. But
on the other hand only honey and bread according to the Rabbis
are allowed to be put up as firewood. Okay? And other stuff
is not allowed to be put up as firewood. So it's a
pretty funny position, it's very ironic. רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer once we're
agreeing that you can learn from the פסוק pasuk that firewood is
okay, then רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer position makes a lot of sense,
okay? That if that could be true about the חמץ chametz and
the honey and the fruit or whatever, then it's also true of
the remnant of the sacrifices. If you put it up as firewood
you're okay. So that's רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer position, but the חכמים
Chachamim do not agree. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. מתניתין דלא כי האי תנא. matnisin d'lo k'hai tanna, Our משנה
mishna that has this debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the
חכמים Chachamim by mixing up the limbs is not like the following
תנא. tanna. Now to appreciate the contrast we're going to say what
I need you to do is to turn the page for a
moment and look at a משנה mishna we're going to get to
very soon. Okay, short דפים, daphim, so we're going to get to
it very soon. So the next משנה mishna says the following, let's
read the next משנה mishna quickly. איברים באיברים בעלי מומין. eivarim b'eivarim
ba'alei mumim. Let's say what got mixed up is not חטאת chatas
and עולה olah but what got mixed up is limbs of two
kosher sacrifices, let's say two kosher עולות, olot, both of which belong
on the altar, except one of them was found out to be
a בעל מום. ba'al mum. So one doesn't belong. It doesn't belong
because it's an עולה olah that's a בעל מום. ba'al mum. So
what you would think you could do the same for רבי אליעזר.
Rabbi Eliezer. Burn it all and say the stuff that's from a
בעל מום ba'al mum is just firewood. Okay, but רבי אליעזר אומר
אם קרב ראש אחד מהן יקרבו כל הראשים כולם. Rabbi Eliezer omer
im karav rosh echad meihen yikrevu kol haroshim kulam. כרעיים של אחד
יקרבו כל הראשים כולם. kra'im shel echad yikrevu kol haroshim kulam. This
is רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer bringing them, you know, about like if
one was already brought we can assume the bad one was brought
and that allows us to bring the rest. You might remember that
we quoted that earlier. But what he does not say is if
one wasn't brought he doesn't let you to just put it all
up and say the bad stuff is firewood. So for some reason
in our משנה mishna when it's a בעל מום ba'al mum issue
you can't treat it just as firewood. The reason the גמרא Gemara
is going to say is it's like an idea of מאיס, ma'is,
you know, it's like something with a מום mum is seen as
stigmatized, it's inappropriate, it's disgusting, it's like it's not just a technical
halachic issue and therefore we don't want to be putting stuff from
an animal that's a בעל מום. ba'al mum. It's funny even though
the מום mum isn't on the limb that we're putting up, right?
And you know and it's not like a limb is more מאיס
ma'is than an actual log of firewood. But the fact that it
comes from an animal that's a בעל מום ba'al mum means רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer saying I don't want you to use this as
firewood. I don't want to rely on that permission of firewood. Okay?
So that's our משנה. mishna. When it's other sacrifices then just say
whatever doesn't belong here is firewood. But when it's a בעל מום
ba'al mum then you don't have that allowance, you need some other
special way of only if one was already brought. That's the structure
of our משנה. mishna. Now back to the גמרא, Gemara, the גמרא's
Gemara going to say that that same division holds according to another
תנא tanna but the debate moves. over one step. Let's take a
look. מתניתין, matnitin so back to the bottom of ע"ז עמוד א'.
ayin zayin amud aleph. So the גמרא gemara says like this, מתניתין
matnisin, דלא d'lo כי האי תנא, k'hai tana. our משנה mishnah is
not like the following תנא. tanna. דתניא, d'tanya, we taught in a
ברייתא. braita. אמר רבי יהודה, amar rabbi yehuda, says Rabbi Yehuda, לא
נחלקו רבי אליעזר וחכמים על איברי חטאת שנתערבו באיברי עולה. lo nechleku
rabbi eliezer v'chachamim al ivrei chatas shenisarvu b'ivrei olah. If this really
was חטאת chatas limbs with עולה olah limbs got mixed up, nobody
disagrees. Though it sounds like they do. No, meaning he doesn't, this
is a different version of the debate. It's our משנה's mishnah version
of the debate has them debating the עולה olah limbs and the
חטאת chatas limbs and has רבי אליעזר rabbi eliezer conceding I wouldn't
do it by a בעל מום. baal mum. The other version of
the debate says no, the עולה olah limbs and the חטאת chatas
limbs, as we said, is more lenient, and everybody agrees you can
put them up and treat the bads, treat the not appropriate stuff
as firewood. Okay, so it's a different version of the debate. When
it's the חטאת chatas and the עולה olah limbs, they all agree,
just, just put it all up and what doesn't belong is firewood.
במה דברים אמורים, bameh devarim amurim, okay, שיקרבו. sheyikrevu. ברובע ונרבע, berovea
v'nirba, now on the other extreme, if it got mixed up was
from an animal that didn't just have a physical blemish but actually
was involved in a sin, an animal that was used in bestiality,
then everybody would agree that you cannot put it up as firewood.
שלא יקרבו. shelo yikrevu. Don't put it up, that's really disgusting, nobody
wants that put up as firewood. במה נחלקו, bameh nechleku, what did
they debate? על איברי עולה תמימה שנתערבו באיברי בעלת מום. al ivrei
olah temimah shenisarvu b'ivrei baalat mum. Like what our משנה mishnah says.
חטאת בעלת מום, chatas baalat mum, mean right? No, עולה בעלת מום.
olah baalat mum. Okay, so the, when it gets mixed up, something
without a blemish with a blemish, which is our משנה. mishnah. Maybe
I misunderstood in the process. Right, our משנה mishnah is saying that
איברי חטאת ivrei chatas שנתערבו shenisarvu with איברי עולה ivrei olah and
it's a מחלוקת machlokes between רבי אליעזר rabbi eliezer and the חכמים
chachamim and then... It's a different version of the debate. Okay, so
this means that someone says like, no, our משנה mishnah is, is
like incorrect? Not incorrect, it's versions of the debate. Everything is by
the oral tradition. My understanding of the debate of רבי אליעזר וחכמים
rabbi eliezer v'chachamim was x, your understanding is it happens all the
time. מיכדי, michdi, I don't understand, לא נחלקו בית הלל ובית שמאי
על דבר זה, lo nechleku beis hillel u'veis shammai al davar zeh,
אלא במה נחלקו, ela bameh nechleku, etc. Okay, so you have the
following, right? You've got the three stages. So רבי rebbi then just
decided to have this version that we have. You've got, you've got
right, you've got חטאת chatas עולה olah mix up. You've got מום
mum and תמים tamim mix up. Okay, and you've got רובע rovea
and נרבע nirba mix up. Quality control at the gate here. Okay,
כשר kasher mixed up with רובע rovea and נרבע. nirba. Okay, each
one of these is more strict because these are worse because they're
physically disgusting, morally disgusting, and not disgusting just wrong. Okay, that's like
the, that's like the hierarchy. Okay, the hierarchy, okay. Wrong, disgusting aesthetically,
and disgusting morally. Good to know that we've got our, our priorities
in the right place. Okay, so according to the משנה, mishnah, okay,
according to the משנה, mishnah, here they debate. And here even רבי
אליעזר rabbi eliezer says don't do it unless you know, don't do
it as firewood. Don't do as firewood, you can do it if
one was already brought, but if one wasn't already brought, you can't
do it as firewood. Okay, and what the, and the גמרא gemara
has a version which is, which is the ברייתא braita says here
everybody says is okay, firewood. Here they debate, okay, where רבי אליעזר
rabbi eliezer says firewood and the חכמים chachamim say no. And here
everybody says is no. All right, so everybody agrees to the hierarchy,
the question is right where they started the debate. Okay, so, okay.
לא נחלקו רבי אליעזר וחכמים על איברי חטאת שנתערבו באיברי עולה שיקרבו.
lo nechleku rabbi eliezer v'chachamim al ivrei chatas shenisarvu b'ivrei olah sheyikrevu.
Everybody says that's okay, treat it as firewood. ברובע ונרבע שלא יקרבו,
berovea v'nirba shelo yikrevu, and the רובע rovea and נרבע nirba don't
treat it, don't offer it up. במה נחלקו, bameh nechleku, what did
they debate? על איברי עולה תמימה שנתערבו באיברי בעלת מום. al ivrei
olah temimah shenisarvu b'ivrei baalat mum. When it is a sacrifice unblemished
with a blemished. שרבי אליעזר אומר יקרבו, she'rabbi eliezer omer yikrevu, in
that case go ahead bring it up, ורואה אני למעלה כאילו הן
עצים, v'ro'eh ani l'malah k'ilu hen eitzim, and I'll see that it's,
I'll pretend it's firewood. וחכמים אומרים לא יקרבו, v'chachamim omrim lo yikrevu,
don't do it. Now, רבי אליעזר, rabbi eliezer, מה ישנא רובע ונרבע
דלא חזי בעל מום נמי לא חזי. mah ishnah rovea v'nirba d'lo
chazi baal mum nami lo chazi. Now what's the difference? Okay, according
to the version of our משנה, mishnah, there's no difference with a
בעל מום baal mum and a רובע ונרבע. rovea v'nirba. By both
of them he agrees, don't do it, okay, so there's no difference.
Okay, this at least was a כשר קרבן, kasher korban, it was
just the wrong one. These can't be כשר קרבנות. kasher korbanos. So
we understand our משנה, mishnah, you don't make a distinction here, they're
both off-limits okay because they're not כשר. kasher. But according to this
approach, what's the difference between a מום mum and רובע ונרבע? rovea
v'nirba? They're both not... כשר kosher קרבנות, korbanot, why is this accepted
for firewood and this not? Okay, so I've already answered that based
on aesthetically versus morally, but let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, says רב הונא, Rav Huna, בדוקין
שבעין ואליבא דרבי עקיבא. Bedukin sheba-ayin va-aliba d'Rabbi Akiva. The reason רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer allows it as firewood is because it's merely not
a that bad of an invalidity, the blemish. It's not a obvious
invalidity, it's only like some cataracts of the eye, and therefore according
to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, when it's not a obvious invalidity, once
it's put on the altar, you don't have to take it off.
Okay, once it's not an obvious blemish. So the reason רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says it's okay is not this issue about aesthetics versus
moral. The reason he says you can put it up as firewood
is cause according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, this type of a
blemish is not totally inappropriate for the altar. Now the irony here
is that what's allowing us to put it on the altar is
that we're looking at it as firewood. But the reason we're saying
it's better than this case is cause it's more fit to be
on the altar as a קרבן. korban. Since the blemish isn't so
obvious, it's more fit to be on the altar as a קרבן.
korban. But we're not putting it on the altar as a קרבן,
korban, we're putting it on the altar as firewood. Okay, but that's
what the גמרא Gemara says. בדוקין שבעין ואליבא דרבי עקיבא דאמר אם
עלו לא ירדו. Bedukin sheba-ayin va-aliba d'Rabbi Akiva d'amar im alu lo
yerdu. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, אימא דאמר רבי עקיבא
בדיעבד. eima d'amar Rabbi Akiva bedi'avad. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says if
you put it up, don't take it off. לכתחילה מי אמר? lechatchila
mi amar? He doesn't let you לכתחילה lechatchila put it up. So
what's only allowing you לכתחילה lechatchila to put it up here is
that you're treating it as firewood. And if so, what's the difference
between the blemish and the animal used in bestiality? So אמר רב
פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, הכא במאי עסקינן כגון שעלו אגבי כבש. hacha
bemai askinan kegon she-alu agabei kevesh. What happened is you didn't put
it up all the way on the fire, you put it on
the ramp. So therefore, according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, you can
move, since it's already effectively on the altar because it's on the
ramp, you can move it to the fire. And again, that applies
to the case of the blemish and not to the case of
the רובע ונרבע. rova venirva. The גמרא Gemara says no, that doesn't
make sense, אי הכי אפילו ביניהו. ei hachi afilu beinihu. If that's
true, it had nothing to do with being mixed up. If it
was already on the ramp and it was this minor blemish, according
to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, you'd be allowed to put it on
the fire even if it hadn't been mixed up. So it has
nothing to do with a minor blemish and a position of רבי
עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. That's not what's going on here. אלא טעמא דרבי
אליעזר מיעט רחמנא מום בם, Ella taima d'Rabbi Eliezer mi'eit Rachmana mum
bam, לא ירצו לכם. lo yeiratze lachem. Okay, the verse is by
a בעל מום, ba'al mum, there's another פסוק, pasuk, כי משחתם בהם
מום בם לא ירצו לכם. ki mashchatam bahem mum bam lo yeiratze
lachem. Their corruption is in them, their blemish is there, they will
not be accepted for you. Okay, so what are we going to
do with מום בם? mum bam? So he says, הכי קאמר, hacha
ka'amar, so says, מיעט רחמנא מום בם, mi'eit Rachmana mum bam, הוא
דלא ירצו הא ידי תערובת ירצו. hu d'lo yeratzu ha yedei ta'arovet
yeratzu. When it's בם, bam, when it's בם, bam, it's only the
blemish is in them, then you can't bring it up. But when
the blemish is, it's a mix and the blemish is in one
of them but not in all of them, so it's not like
singled out this is the thing with the blemish, then actually it's
okay to be brought up. So according to this, it's not being
brought up as firewood necessarily. It's actually saying that you can bring
this up as an offering if the blemish is not specifically and
identified to this. Okay, so that's the reading. It's actually seems to
be moving away from the firewood idea. You got the point? When
is it you can't bring it up on the altar? When the
blemish is specifically in this. In this case when it's mixed up,
you can bring it up on the altar. Okay, מום בם הוא
דלא ירצו הא ידי תערובת ירצו. mum bam hu d'lo yeratzu ha
yedei ta'arovet yeratzu. So saying the word ירצו, yeratzu, will be accepted,
is saying a lot more than treating it as firewood. It's saying
in this case when it's mixed up, it's actually acceptable to be
offered. ורבנן, Ve-rabbanan, what would the rabbis say back? מום בם הוא
דלא ירצו הא דעבר מומא ירצו. mum bam hu d'lo yeratzu ha
d'avar muma yeratzu. No, מום בם mum bam doesn't mean when it's
in them specifically versus being mixed. It means as long as the
blemish remains. So if something has a passing blemish, it'll be acceptable
once the blemish goes away. So מום בם mum bam means the
מום mum is present. It doesn't mean it's specifically that and not
somewhere else. רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, מבם בהם. mibam bahem. רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says it says here בהם bahem and here it says
בם, bam, so those two words are telling you one is saying
it's only a problem when the blemish is present and the other
is saying it's only a problem when the blemish is specifically identified,
not when it's mixed up with something else. ורבנן בם בהם לא
דרשי, Ve-rabbanan bam bahem lo darshi, and they the rabbis say that's
not what it's about. Okay, so this is a lovely דרשה, derasha,
that's why we're saying that the blemish is better, but according to
this, it's not firewood. According to this, it's actually an acceptable offering
in this case. So the גמרא Gemara says, that's pretty basically what
the גמרא Gemara asks, אי הכי רואה? ei hachi roeh? So what
does he mean I'm going to look at it like it's firewood?
הא רחמנא אכשריה. ha Rachmana achshereh. The תורה Torah said it's כשר.
kosher. It's כשר kosher as an offering ממש mamash it's כשר kosher
to be brought up. So he says לדיבריהם קאמר להו, L'divreihem kamar
lahu, he's saying to the rabbis, as from your perspective. לדידי, Lididi,
as far as I'm concerned, רחמנא אכשריה, Rachmana achsherei, the תורה Torah
says that in this case it's כשר. Kosher. לדידכו, Lididchu, from your
perspective, אודו לי מיהת בשר בעל מום כעצים דמי, odu li mihat
basar baal mum ke'eitzim dami, at least why can't you treat this
as firewood? From my perspective, it's ממש mamash כשר Kosher to be
brought up once it's mixed up. But from your perspective, why not
treat it as firewood since according to the ברייתא, Beraita, you're okay
with a חטאת Chatat and עולה Olah treating it as firewood, why
don't you want to treat this as firewood? And the rabbis say
back: מידי דהוה אבשר חטאת. midei dehavei abasar Chatat. Like by the
חטאת, Chatat, רבנן, Rabbanan, the rabbis would say back, הכא מאיסי התם
לא מאיסי. hacha meisi hatam lo meisi. Okay, in that case, in
one case it's disgusting, in this case it's disgusting, and in the
חטאת Chatat case it wasn't disgusting. Okay, so that's the way the
גמרא Gemara explains it. So in the end, the גמרא Gemara explains
according to this version, according to this version a מום mum and
a רובע ונרבע rova v'nirva are equally not good and you can't
do firewood, and we'll see in the משנה Mishna what you can
do. But according to this version, okay, normally you could do firewood.
According to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, a מום mum you could do
firewood, but not רובע ונרבע. rova v'nirva. And the גמרא Gemara says,
what's the difference? In the end, the גמרא Gemara says because according
to him, actually, a מום mum when its pieces are mixed up
is actually כשר. Kosher. Okay, but what you could have said is
a difference between how disgusting it is: aesthetically disgusting versus morally disgusting.
But in the end, what the גמרא Gemara says is according to
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, the line of difference is that actually a
blemish, when the pieces are mixed up, actually is כשר Kosher and
can be offered up as a sacrifice. Okay, so now let's look
at the next משנה, Mishna, which actually deals with the case of
our משנה's Mishna version of the debate, that a blemish cannot be
brought up as firewood. So what do you do when it gets
mixed up? איברים באיברים בעלי מומין. Eivarim b'eivarim baalei mumin. Let's say
it gets mixed up, all עולה Olah pieces, but one came from
an עולה Olah that has a blemish. And again, because of this
idea that it's disgusting, we're not going to use it as firewood.
So what are you going to do? So רבי אליעזר אומר אם
קרב ראש אחד מהם יקרבו כל הראשים. Rabbi Eliezer omer im kareiv
rosh echad meihem yikrevu kol haroshim. Let's say it was only one
animal obviously that was bad. So he says, once one of the
heads got brought up, you weren't supposed to, but if you did,
we're going to assume that that was the bad one and that's
going to now allow us to bring the rest. By the way,
now of course you know these are all funny, like yeah we're
just going to assume it all worked out. Okay, but the logic
here could be that since really you're allowed to do it because
of firewood, and the only reason we're not doing it is because
it's disgusting, so as long as we get rid of the disgusting
factor, you can do it. The way you get rid of the
disgusting factor is you basically say it was already done. We're just
going to assume what happened happened, it was already done, so you
don't have to feel right now that you're putting on the מזבח
mizbeach something from a blemish because you just say, you know what,
let's just pretend and assume or whatever that that already took place
in the past. So that is going to allow it to be
done. כרעיים של אחד מהם יקרבו כל הכרעיים. Krayim shel echad meihem
yikrevu kol hakrayim. If you brought the legs of one of them,
you can bring all of the legs because you could assume that
the blemished one had already been done. וחכמים אומרים אפילו קרבו כולם
חוץ מאחד מהם יצא לבית השריפה. Vachachamim omrim afilu karvu kulam chutz
me'echad meihem yeitzei l'veit hasreifa. The opposite. If even if you brought
all, let's assume it was a thousand, 999 legs, and you're left
with one leg, you can't just say, oh, I'm going to assume
I've already done the bad one. No, this might be the bad
one, and because this might be the bad one, you're not לכתחילה
lechatchila allowed to put it on the מזבח. mizbeach. Okay, so the
חכמים Chachamim again are very strict. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer wants to
find some type of a solution. אמר רב אלעזר, Amar Rav Elazar,
said רב אלעזר, Rav Elazar, the אמורא. Amora. לא הכשיר רבי אליעזר,
Lo hichshir Rabbi Eliezer, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer the תנא Tanna when
he allows it, if one head was brought to bring the rest
of the heads, אלא שנים שנים. ela shnayim shnayim. You have to
bring two at a time. And then you could say, if you're
bringing two at a time, you have two things to say. On
the one hand, I'm going to assume that the bad one was
already brought. On the other hand, and what allows me even further
to assume that is of the two heads here, I know that
one head is definitely okay. And therefore I can assume if one
head is okay, reasonably the other head is probably also okay. So
it's the combination of those two sort of ways of thinking. So,
אבל אחד אחד לא. aval echad echad lo. מתיב רבי ירמיה, Mative
Rabbi Yirmeyah, רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmeyah asks: וחכמים אומרים אפילו קרבו כולם
חוץ מאחד מהם יצא לבית השריפה. Vachachamim omrim afilu karvu kulam chutz
me'echad meihem yeitzei l'veit hasreifa. So the חכמים Chachamim say even if
all of them are offered except for one, you have to go
ahead and burn it. Which means according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer,
what would you do? You brought all 999 and you were left
with one. What would you do for רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer with
that one you were left with? Put it up on the מזבח.
mizbeach. But you're only putting one up. You're not putting up a
pair. And we're trying to say that according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi
Eliezer, you have to always put them up as a pair. So
it doesn't sound that way from the משנה. Mishna. From the משנה,
Mishna, it sounds like even if you're left with one, you put
that one up. So אמר ליה רבי ירמיה בר תחליפא אסברא לך:
Amar lei Rabbi Yirmeyah bar Tachlifa asbra lach: מאי אחד זוג אחד.
mai echad zug echad. No, when it says if you're only left
with one you can put it up, it means if you're only
left with one pair. Okay, so again, this is obviously reading something
into the משנה, Mishna, it's not in the משנה. Mishna. But now
the claim is that with רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer working with this
idea in cases where you can't bring it up as firewood, you
can still bring it up if you can assume that it was
already done. already happened, even if one thing happened you can now
do it. Now we're claiming as long as you're bringing them up
in pairs and then you can assume since one is good we
can assume the other one is good as well. Okay. Now we
move from mixing up limbs to mixing up blood. Okay, and this
is a very important גמרא Gemara for all like laws of כשרות
Kashrus and mixtures and so on, and we'll just start it with
the משנה Mishna and we'll pick up with this tomorrow. So, let's
take a look at the משנה. Mishna. דם שנתערב במים. Dam shenitarev
bemayim. You have a drop of your קרבן korban blood, you caught
it in a כלי, kli, you have to catch it in a
כלי, kli, but then it got mixed up in water. Okay, somehow
from your bowl that you caught the blood, you spilled water in
it or you spilled from it into water. Can you still throw
it on the altar? So this is like, you know, classically when
we talk about mixtures, we want to get rid of the bad,
right? We want to say, if there's a drop of חזיר chazer
that falls into my soup, do I have to throw out my
soup? Okay. And well, can you still taste it? If you can
still taste it, it's there, you got to throw out your soup.
But what if you want the thing, what if you want the
thing that dropped in to still be there? So if a drop
of the blood, if a drop of blood fell into your chicken
soup, you don't want the blood to be there. But if the
drop of the blood fell into your water and you want to
throw it on the altar, you want to say the blood is
still there. Okay. So what is going to allow you to say
the blood is still there? So if we were talking about eating
and food, we would say, could you taste it? If you can
taste the blood, it's still there. And then maybe, and that might
say, that will let you throw it on the altar. But here,
we're not treating this as food. And if we're not treating this
as food, we're not going to focus on taste. So what do
you think of our five senses is the primary sense we use
for interpreting the world and for experiencing the world? Don't look ahead.
Okay. So, right, our eyes. Correct. Okay. Sight is our primary way
of getting information and looking at whatever, and I even saying looking
at whatever, experiencing the world. So in the world of taste, in
a mixture, what matters is, in the world of food, in a
mixture, what matters is, can you taste it? Okay. But in all
other areas, or almost all other areas, when we're dealing with mixtures,
what much more matters is what, whether it can be seen and
not whether it can be tasted. So that's a really important conceptual
difference. Although from what I understand from all these tests that they've
done or whatever, experiences that they've done, taste is actually the third
most important part of how you experience food. That the first two
are I think like, like sight and texture or something I think,
before you actually get to taste. So it's actually quite fascinating even
by food. But anyway. Okay, דם שנתערב במים. Dam shenitarev bemayim. So
blood gets mixed up with water. אם יש בו מראית דם, Im
yesh bo mar'it dam, if it still has the appearance of blood.
Now what does the appearance of blood mean? Does it mean that
there's a little reddish tint to the water so you can tell
blood is there? Or does it mean the water looks like blood?
Right? For the water to look like blood, then there has to
be a lot of blood there. So exactly what מראית דם, mar'it
dam, the simple sense of מראית דם mar'it dam means like not
that it looks like blood but like you can sense that the
blood is there. Okay. So כשר, kasher, it's kosher. So again, the
key important principle here is that when you're dealing with mixtures when
the focus is not food, you go by appearances. And since the
blood can still be sensed and seen to some degree, it's there
and you can use this to put on the altar. נתערב ביין.
Nitarev beyayin. Now let's say it gets mixed up with wine. So
you can't tell it because it's a dark liquid. So do we
just say it disappeared? So here's a big חידוש. chidush. רואין אותו
כאילו הוא מים. Ro'in oto ke'ilu hu mayim. You say to yourself,
if this wine had been water, would the blood be visible? And
if the answer is yes, had it been water I would have
been able to sense the presence of some blood, then even though
now it's not visible, you can say that the blood is still
present, which is a big חידוש. chidush. What lets you say that?
In the current reality, it's not present, it's not visible. What lets
you say the blood is still seen as present? נתערב בדם בהמה,
Nitarev bedam behema, okay, או בדם החיה, O bedam hachaya, and let's
say it's blood with blood. Let's say it gets mixed up with,
with blood of just a non-sanctified animal or even of a חיה,
chaya, of a deer. רואין אותו כאילו הוא מים. Ro'in oto ke'ilu
hu mayim. Again, like we said by the wine, if, had it
been water, it would have been detectable, then even though it's not
detectable, we'll see it's still there. Now I should say that when
it comes to being strict, we do this all the time, right?
Let's say you get a drop of טרף treif chicken soup gets
mixed up with your kosher chicken soup. What do we say you,
when do we say it goes out of existence? It's בטל. batel.
When it's less than one in sixty. Now the one in sixty
number comes from whether it would be tastable if it was mixed
up in something else. But when it's chicken and chicken, it's not
you can't taste it, you know, you can't right away you can't
taste it because it's all the same. And nevertheless we use the
model of same and different, you know, in order to say whether
we're going to be strict and say don't eat the chicken soup.
Since this טרף treif chicken soup would be tastable if the pot
was just clear water, it would be forbidden, it's forbidden even when
it gets mixed up with your chicken soup. with the כשר kosher
chicken soup. Here we're saying it to be lenient. Since this blood
would have been detectable in water and would have been seen as
present and you could put it on the altar, even when it's
in wine or in blood and not detectable, we're going to define
it as present and you can put it in the altar. Very
strange. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda Omer, now Rabbi Yehuda says אין
דם מבטל דם. Ein Dam Mevatel Dam. He's even more lenient. He
says even if there's a ton of blood and had it been
water the stuff would not be visible, blood and blood never loses
its identity. So if a drop of blood mixed up in a
million gallons, even though it would completely have stopped being visible if
it was water, if it's all blood and blood, the blood is
always there. And you could always put it on the altar. Now,
נתערב בדם פסולין, nitrav bedam pesulin, if it gets mixed up with
the blood of invalid sacrifices, then even if we consider it still
present, you're not allowed to put the blood of invalid sacrifices on
the altar. So in that case, you have no choice and ישפך
לאמה, yishafech la'amah, spill it out into like the gutter that takes
it out of the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. התם בדם התמצית, hatam
bedam hatamtzit, let's say it gets mixed up with blood that is
not from the life-force blood. Okay, similarly ישפך לאמה, yishafech la'amah, spill
it out in the gutter, it might be considered present, but you
can't put it on the altar. רבי אליעזר מכשיר, Rabbi Eliezer machshir,
Rabbi Eliezer says actually in that case I'll let you put on
the altar. So that's a fascinating question. What, why can you put
water and wine on the altar when it's part of the mixture,
but these types of bloods you can't put on the altar? What's
the debate? אם לא נמלך ונתן כשר, Im lo nimlach venatan kasher,
and the הלכה halacha is everybody agrees that after the fact it
is kosher. Since it's still considered present, if you went and put
it on the altar it's kosher, but with these mixtures of this
non-life-force blood, there's a debate of whether you're allowed to put on
the altar and we'll have to see what that debate is about.
But that's sort of secondary, the primary focus here is this fascinating
issue of mixtures, which as I said parallels the world of mixtures
of food, but with two important differences. Number one here it's about
sight, it's not about taste. And number two is that here even
when it's not visible, we treat it as visible to be lenient.
By food when it's not tastable, we might treat it as if
the taste is present to be strict when it's all the same
type of thing. But here we're going to treat it as still
present to be lenient and to let you use it. Okay, so
there's a very important משנה, Mishna, we will discuss this tomorrow.